Hello, I’m Warren Robins of MediDent FS,
I’m an income protection specialist for
dentists and medical doctors.
Todays topic is, Who offers the best income
protection for dentists?
The answer to that question is, not surprisingly,
it depends on your specific needs
but there are some general guidelines that
can save you a lot of money,
when you’re choosing income protection,
so if you already have a policy or if, quite
sensibly you’re looking to take it out,
keep watching,
as spending a couple of minutes here could
seriously reduce your future spending on income
protection.
As a dentist, there are a lot of people competing
for your business and this is certainly the
case with income protection.
The most popular insurers in dentistry are
Dentists Provident and Wesleyan, both of which
heavily trumpet the benefits you get from
their expertise in the dental and medical
fields.
While I would totally agree that a detailed
knowledge of the dental field is a valuable
asset when advising on dentists income protection,
that knowledge is also available through independent
brokers specialising in dentists,
like MediDent FS,
with the added advantage that they don't offer
policies from just one insurance company.
If you want to get an unbiased analysis of
how Dentists Provident or Wesleyan policies
compare to other insurers,
you obviously won't get that from their advisors.
You can expect both to tell you that their
policy is the best for dentists but realistically,
what else are they going to say?
A dental specialist independent adviser however,
is not tied to one insurance company,
so can offer unbiased advice on all the options
that are available
and they can almost certainly also offer significant
savings in both the monthly premium and the
full policy term cost.
If you really want the best policy, it makes
sense to speak to Wesleyan and / or Dentist
Provident
but then make sure
that you also speak to a specialist independent
broker as well.
That way you'll be making a fully informed
decision on who to take your Dentist income
protection with
and considering how long these policies run
for,
it’s a decision you really don’t want
to get wrong because if you do
it could easily cost you an extra £40k, even
for a modest IP policy.
I know that sounds crazy but that’s the
reality.
As long as you are comparing income protection
policies offering Own Occupation Cover, which
pays out if you can’t work as a dentist,
the core benefit is essentially the same with
any insurer,
dental specialist or not, as they are all
regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority.
This means that, unless you have specific
factors, such as working through your own
Ltd Company,
you can look for the best value policy available
but, you’ll be surprised
to hear, this doesn’t
always mean the lowest starting premium
and I’ll explain why.
The reason is, when insurers apply the annual
cover increases, the premium goes up by more
than the cover, with the exception of one
insurer
and there are more than 10 different increase
methods used by insurers
and here are some examples .
The result is that for any given cover increase,
there will be quite a range of different premium
increases.
Finding out which method is used by an insurer
is really difficult, unless you talk to me,
because this information is buried deep in
the policy documents, which you’re only
given AFTER you’ve taken a policy out.
The best way to illustrate this is to show
you what happens to the premiums of different
insurers with the same amount of annual cover
increase,
if they all started at the same initial premium.
Obviously they don’t start at the same cost
in reality but this does show the impact of
the different increase method on the long
term cost.
As you can see here, the age costed increase
method, used by both Wesleyan and Dentists
Provident
becomes increasingly expensive as you get
older, leading to a much bigger full term
cost,
compared to most other increase methods apart
from Vitality but that's only half the story.
A number of insurers use the same increase
method, so Zurich, Aviva and LV all follow
the L&G line.
If you apply the different increase methods
to real premiums, it makes interesting reading
for dentists.
This projection shows total costs as follows.
Holloway at just under £29k, Dentist Provident
at just under £69k and Wesleyan at over £85k,
so massive cost differences.
In theory, you can see the cost impact I’ve
shown here, on insurer quotation documents,
as they have to include the full term cost
but here’s the thing.
Insurers write in disclaimers, so the total
costs they show assume the starting premium
does this…………it never changes, so,
completely unrealistic.
A realistic cost, if the annual cost of living
increases at the same level as the last 35
years, just 3.6%,
can be between 2 and 6 times what’s shown
on the quote, depending on the insurer.
These disclaimers are subtle, as you can see,
where I’ve highlighted the one used by Dentists
Provident
but what they hide is pretty shocking.
The premium differences shown in my example
are not unusual.
Wesleyan and Dentist Provident starting premiums
are normally quite a bit more expensive than
some other insurance companies, which only
exaggerates the age costed increase method.
Using data from dentists I've spoken to over
the last 3 to 4 years, Dentists Provident
averages around 40% more expensive, and Wesleyan
averages around 55% more expensive, versus
the best available starting premium.
When you can work out realistic overall costs,
what you see is that certain insurers are
normally very expensive, such as Wesleyan
& Dentists Provident,
Vitality, Cirencester Friendly and British
Friendly Society,
so unless you’re happy to overpay, you can
normally rule them out
but there are plenty of other insurers to
choose from,
all offering equivalent cover to that offered
by dental specialist insurers.
OK, if you speak to an independent insurance
adviser, which insurance company are they
going to recommend?
Well, that depends entirely on your individual
circumstances,
are you a sole trader or do you work through
a Ltd company for instance,
so in reality there is no single insurer that’s
the best choice for every dentist.
Also, how the insurance is set up is equally
important and insurers vary
in their competitiveness
for different cover arrangements and this
also changes over time,
so there are many variables.
The key point is to get expert independent
advice, from an adviser
that can forecast and compare realistic full
term costs
and that is what we pride ourselves on at
MediDent FS.
Oh, and by the way, a word of warning.
There are two types of independent insurance
broker available, regarding the premiums that
they charge.
The first type charges exactly the same premium
as you would pay going direct to the insurance
company, such as MediDent FS.
The second type receives a boosted commission
amount, which is paid for by increasing the
monthly premiums,
typically by 10 to 20%, which will cost you
an enormous amount extra over the policy term.
Just ask a broker if their premiums are loaded
and if they are,
I suggest you look elsewhere.
Thanks for watching, I’m Warren Robins,
the income protection specialist for Dentists
& doctors.